{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "1.8","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["8.1 × 109/L","16.7 × 109/L","21.0 × 109/L","80.8 × 109/L"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "16.7 × 109/L","explanation": "The formula for correcting the WBC count for the presence of NRBCs is: Total WBC × 100 or (21.0 × 100) ÷ 126 = 16.7 × 109/L where total WBC = WBCs × 109/L, 100 is the number of WBCs counted in the differential, and 126 is the sum of NRBCs plus WBCs counted in the differential"},"question": "A 19-year-old man came to the emergency department with severe joint pain, fatigue, cough, and fever. Review the following laboratory results: WBCs 21.0 × 109/L RBCs 3.23 × 1012/L Hgb 9.6 g/dL PLT 252 × 109/L Differential: 17 band neutrophils; 75 segmented neutrophils; 5 lymphocytes; 2 monocytes; 1 eosinophil; 26 NRBCs What is the corrected WBC count?","reference": "Hematology/Calculate/WBCs corrected for NRBCs/2"},{"choices": ["4.0 × 109/L","8.0 × 109/L","20.0 × 109/L","200.0 × 109/L"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "20.0 × 109/L","explanation": "The formula for calculating manual cell counts using a hemacytometer is: # cells counted × 10 (depth factor) × dilution factor ÷ area counted in mm2 or (80 × 10 × 100) ÷ 4 = 20,000/μL or 20.0 × 109/"},"question": "A manual WBC count is performed. Eighty WBCs are counted in the four large corner squares of a Neubauer hemacytometer. The dilution is 1:100. What is the total WBC count?","reference": "Hematology/Calculate/Cell count/2"},{"choices": ["27.8 × 109/L","62.5 × 109/L","125.0 × 109/L","250.0 × 109/L"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "250.0 × 109/L","explanation": "Regardless of the cell or fluid type, the formula for calculating manual cell counts using a hemacytometer is: # cells counted × 10 (depth factor) × dilution factor ÷ area counted in mm2 or (125 × 10 × 200) ÷ 1 = 250,000/μL or 250.0 × 109/"},"question": "A manual RBC count is performed on pleural fluid. The RBC count in the large center square of the Neubauer hemacytometer is 125, and the dilution is 1:200. What is the total RBC count?","reference": "Hematology/Calculate/Cell count/2"},{"choices": ["A", "B", "C", "D"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "A","explanation": "WBC identification is facilitated by analysis of the impedance, conductance, and light- scattering properties of WBCs. The scatterplot represents the relationship between volume (x-axis) and light scatter (y-axis). Monocytes account for the dots in section A, neutrophils are represented in section B, eosinophils are represented in section C, and lymphocytes are denoted in section D"},"question": "Review the scatterplot of WBCs shown. Which section of the scatterplot denotes the number of monocytes?","reference": "Hematology/Apply basic principles to interpret results/Automated cell counting/2"},{"choices": ["MCV/perform reticulocyte count","Hct/perform manual Hct","WBC/perform manual WBC count","Hgb/perform serum–saline replacement"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "WBC/perform manual WBC count","explanation": "When an automated WBC count is performed using a hematology analyzer, RBCs are lysed to allow enumeration of WBCs. Sickle cells are often resistant to lysis within the limited time frame (less than 1 minute), during which the RBCs are exposed to the lysing reagent and the WBCs are subsequently counted. As a result, the nonlysed RBCs are counted along with WBCs, and this falsely increases the WBC count. When an automated cell counting analyzer indicates a review flag for the WBC count and sickle cells are noted on peripheral blood smear analysis, a manual WBC count must be performed. The manual method allows optimal time for sickle cell lysis and accurate enumeration of WBCs"},"question": "Review the following automated CBC values. WBC = 17.5 × 109/L (flagged) MCV = 86.8 fL RBC = 2.89 × 1012/L MCH = 28.0 pg Hgb = 8.1 g/dL MCHC = 32.3% Hct = 25.2% PLT = 217 × 109/L Many sickle cells were observed on review of the peripheral blood smear. On the basis of this finding and the results provided, what automated parameter of this patient is most likely inaccurate, and what follow-up test should be done to accurately assess this parameter?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge to identify sources of error/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["Macrocytic anemia","Microcytic anemia","Liver disease","Normal values for a 2-day-old infant"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Normal values for a 2-day-old infant","explanation": "During the first week of life, an infant has an average Hct of 55 mL/dL. This value drops to a mean of 43 mL/dL by the first month of life. The mean MCV of the first week is 108 fL; after 2 months, the average MCV is 96 fL. The mean WBC count during the first week is approximately 18 × 109/L, and this drops to an average of 10.8 × 109/L after the first month. The PLT count in newborns falls within the same normal range as in adults"},"question": "Review the following CBC results for a 2-day-old infant: WBC = 15.2 × 109/L MCV = 105 fL RBC = 5.30 × 1012/L MCH = 34.0 pg Hgb = 18.5 g/dL MCHC = 33.5% Hct = 57.9% PLT = 213 × 109/L These results indicate:","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Normal values/2"},{"choices": ["Infectious mononucleosis","Monocytosis","CLL","β-Thalassemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Infectious mononucleosis","explanation": "Lymphocytosis with numerous atypical lymphocytes is a hallmark finding consistent with the diagnosis of infectious mononucleosis. The automated results demonstrated abnormal WBC subpopulations, specifically lymphocytosis as well as monocytosis. However, on peripheral blood smear examination, 60 atypical lymphocytes and only six monocytes were noted. Atypical lymphocytes are often misclassified by automated cell counters as monocytes. Therefore, the automated analyzer differential must not be released and the manual differential count must be relied on for diagnostic interpretation"},"question": "Review the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 21-year-old college student. WBC differential: 5 band neutrophils; 27 segmented neutrophils; 60 atypical lymphocytes; 6 monocytes; 1 eosinophil; 1 basophil What is the presumptive diagnosis?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge to identify sources of error/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["Leukemoid reaction","CML","AML","Megaloblastic leukemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "CML","explanation": "The “+++++” on the printout indicates that the WBC count exceeds the upper linearity of the analyzer (greater than 99.9 × 109/L). This markedly elevated WBC count, combined with the spectrum of immature granulocytic cells seen on peripheral blood smear examination, indicates the diagnosis of CML"},"question": "Review the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 61-year-old woman. WBC differential: 14 band neutrophils; 50 segmented neutrophils; 7 lymphocytes; 4 monocytes; 10 metamyelocytes; 8 myelocytes; 1 promyelocyte; 3 eosinophils; 3 basophils; 2 NRBCs/100 WBCs What is the presumptive diagnosis?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["WBC and relative percentages of WBC populations","RBCs and PLTs","Hgb and Hct","None of the automated counts can be released without follow-up verification"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "None of the automated counts can be released without follow-up verification","explanation": "All of the automated results have “R,” or review, flags indicated; none can be released without manual verification procedures. The specimen must be diluted to bring the WBC count within the linearity range of the analyzer. When enumerating the RBC count, the analyzer does not lyse the WBCs and, in fact, includes them in the RBC count. As such, the RBC count is falsely elevated because of the increased number of WBCs. Therefore, after an accurate WBC count has been obtained, this value can be subtracted from the RBC count to obtain the true RBC count. For example, using the values for this patient: Step 1: Obtain an accurate WBC count by diluting the sample 1:10. WBC = 41.0 × 10 (dilution) = 410 × 109/L Step 2: Convert this value to cells per 1012 to subtract from the RBC count. 410 × 109/L = 0.41 × 1012/L Step 3: Subtract the WBC count from the RBC count to get the accurate RBC count. 3.28 (original RBC) – 0.41 (true WBC) = 2.87 × 1012/L = accurate RBC The Hct may be obtained by microhematocrit centrifugation. The true MCV may be obtained by using the standard formula: MCV = (Hct ÷ RBC) × 10 where RBC = RBC count in millions per microliter. Additionally, the PLT count must be verified by smear estimate or performed manually"},"question": "Review the automated results from the previous question. Which parameters can be released without further follow-up verification procedures?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge to identify sources of error/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["Redraw blood sample using a sodium citrate tube; multiply PLTs × 1.11","Dilute WBCs 1:10; multiply × 10","Perform plasma blank Hgb to correct for lipemia","Warm specimen at 37°C for 15 minutes; rerun specimen"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Redraw blood sample using a sodium citrate tube; multiply PLTs × 1.11","explanation": "The PLT clumping phenomenon is often induced in vitro by the anticoagulant EDTA.Redrawing a sample from the patient by using a sodium citrate tube usually corrects this phenomenon and allows for accurate PLT enumeration. The PLT count must be multiplied by 1.11 to adjust for the amount of sodium citrate. PLT clumps cause a spurious decrease in the PLT count by automated methods. The WBC value has an “R” (review) flag because the PLT clumps have been falsely counted as WBCs; therefore, a manual WBC count is indicated"},"question": "Refer to the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 45-year-old man. What follow-up verification procedure is indicated before these results can be released?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge to identify sources of error/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["Redraw specimen using a sodium citrate tube; multiply PLTs × 1.11","Dilute WBCs 1:10; multiply × 10","Perform plasma blank Hgb to correct for lipemia","Warm the specimen at 37°C for 15 minutes; rerun the specimen"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Warm the specimen at 37°C for 15 minutes; rerun the specimen","explanation": "The presence of high-titer cold agglutinin in a patient with cold AIHA will interfere with automated cell counting. The most remarkable findings are falsely elevated MCV, MCH, and MCHC, as well as falsely decreased RBC count. The patient’s RBCs will quickly agglutinate in vitro when exposed to ambient temperatures below body temperature. To correct for this phenomenon, the EDTA tube should be incubated at 37°C for 15 to 30 minutes, and then the specimen should be rerun"},"question": "Refer to the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 52-year-old woman. What follow-up verification procedure is indicated before these results can be released?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge to identify sources of error/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["Perform a manual Hct and redraw the sample using a sodium citrate tube; multiply PLTs × 1.11","Dilute WBCs 1:10; multiply × 10","Perform plasma blank Hgb to correct for lipemia","Warm the specimen at 37°C for 15 minutes; rerun the specimen"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Perform plasma blank Hgb to correct for lipemia","explanation": "The rule of thumb regarding the Hgb/Hct correlation dictates that Hgb × 3 ≈ Hct (± 3). This rule has been violated in this patient; therefore, a follow-up verification procedure is indicated. Additionally, MCHC is markedly elevated in these results, and an explanation for falsely increased Hgb should be sought. Lipemia can be visualized by centrifuging the EDTA tube and observing for a milky white plasma. To correct for the presence of lipemia, a plasma Hgb value (baseline Hgb) should be ascertained by using the patient’s plasma and subsequently subtracted from the original falsely elevated Hgb value. The following formula can be used to correct for lipemia: Whole blood Hgb – [(Plasma Hgb) (1 – Hct/100)] = Corrected Hg"},"question": "Refer to the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 33-year-old woman. What follow-up verification procedure is indicated before these results can be released?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge to identify sources of error/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["Dilute WBCs 1:10; multiply × 10","Redraw the sample using a sodium citrate tube; multiply WBCs × 1.11","Prepare buffy coat peripheral blood smears, and perform a manual differential","Warm specimen at 37°C for 15 minutes; rerun specimen"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Prepare buffy coat peripheral blood smears, and perform a manual differential","explanation": "The markedly decreased WBC count (0.2 × 109/L) indicates that a manual differential is necessary and that very few leukocytes will be available for differential cell counting. To increase the yield and thereby facilitate counting, differential smears should be prepared by using the buffy coat technique"},"question": "Refer to the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 48-year-old man. What follow-up verification procedure is indicated before the five-part WBC differential results can be released?","reference": "Hematology/Select course of action/Instrumentation/3"},{"choices": ["ALL","CLL","Infectious mononucleosis","Myelodysplastic syndrome"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "CLL","explanation": "CLL is a disease of older adults, classically associated with an elevated WBC count and relative and absolute lymphocytosis. CLL is twice as common in men, and smudge cells (WBCs with little or no surrounding cytoplasm) are usually present in the peripheral blood smear. CLL may occur with or without anemia or thrombocytopenia. The patient’s age and lack of blasts rule out ALL. Similarly, the patient’s age and lack of atypical lymphocytes make infectious mononucleosis unlikely. Myelodysplastic syndromes may involve the erythroid, granulocytic, or megakaryocytic cell lines but not the lymphoid cells"},"question": "Review the following CBC results for a 70-year-old man: WBC = 58.2 × 109/L MCV = 98 fL RBC = 2.68 × 1012/L MCH = 31.7 pg Hgb = 8.5 g/dL MCHC = 32.6% Hct = 26.5 mL/dL% PLT = 132 × 109/L Differential: 96 lymphocytes; 2 band neutrophils; 2 segmented neutrophils; 25 smudge cells/100 WBCs What is the most likely diagnosis on the basis of these values?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/2"},{"choices": ["DIC","HE (ovalocytosis)","Cirrhosis","Hgb C disease"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "HE (ovalocytosis)","explanation": "The finding of ovalocytes as the predominant RBC morphology in peripheral blood is consistent with the diagnosis of HE, or ovalocytosis. This disorder is relatively common and can range in severity from an asymptomatic carrier state to homozygous HE with severe hemolysis. The most common clinical subtype is associated with no or minimal hemolysis. Therefore, HE is usually associated with a normal RBC histogram and cell indices and will go unnoticed without microscopic evaluation of the peripheral blood smear"},"question": "Refer to the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 28-year-old woman who had undergone preoperative laboratory testing. A manual WBC differential was requested by her physician. The WBC differential was not significantly different from the automated five-part differential; however, the medical laboratory scientist noted 3+ elliptocytes/ovalocytes while reviewing the RBC morphology. What is the most likely diagnosis for this patient?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/2"},{"choices": ["Osmotic fragility test","Hgb electrophoresis","G6PD assay","Methemoglobin reduction test"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Osmotic fragility test","explanation": "The osmotic fragility test is indicated as a confirmatory test for the presence of numerous spherocytes, and individuals with HS have an increased osmotic fragility. MCHC is elevated in greater than 50% of patients with spherocytosis, and this parameter can be used as a clue to the presence of HS. Spherocytes have a decreased surface:volume ratio, probably resulting from mild cellular dehydration"},"question": "A 25-year-old woman presented with symptoms of jaundice, acute cholecystitis, and an enlarged spleen. On investigation, numerous gallstones were discovered. Review the following CBC results: WBC = 11.1 × 109/L MCV = 100 fL RBC = 3.33 × 1012/L MCH = 34.5 pg Hgb = 11.5 g/dL MCHC = 37.5% Hct = 31.6 mL/dL PLT = 448 × 109/L WBC differential: 13 band neutrophils; 65 segmented neutrophils; 15 lymphocytes; 6 monocytes; 1 eosinophil RBC morphology: 3+ spherocytes, 1+ polychromasia What follow-up laboratory test would provide valuable information for this patient?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/3"},{"choices": ["IDA","PV","Sideroblastic anemia","β-thalassemia minor"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "β-thalassemia minor","explanation": "β-thalassemia minor can be easily detected by noting an abnormally elevated RBC count and Hct that does not correlate with the elevated RBC count, in conjunction with a decreased MCV. Although thalassemia and IDA are both microcytic, hypochromic processes, thalassemia can be differentiated from IDA because in IDA the RBC count, Hgb, and Hct values are usually decreased along with MCV. Although the RBC count is increased in PV, Hct must also be greater than 50% for a diagnosis of PV to be considered"},"question": "Refer to the following scatterplot, histograms, and automated values for a 53-year-old man who had undergone preoperative laboratory testing. What is the most likely diagnosis for this patient?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/3"},{"choices": ["Osmotic fragility test","Hgb electrophoresis","Sugar water test","Bone marrow examination"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hgb electrophoresis","explanation": "The findings of moderate anemia, numerous target cells seen on the peripheral blood smear, and the presence of NRBCs are often associated with hemoglobinopathies. Hgb electrophoresis at alkaline pH is a commonly performed test to correctly diagnose the type of hemoglobinopathy"},"question": "Review the following CBC results: WBC = 11.0 × 109/L MCV = 85.0 fL RBC = 3.52 × 1012/L MCH = 28.4 pg Hgb = 10.0 g/dL MCHC = 33.4% Hct = 29.9 mL/dL PLT = 155 × 109/L 12 NRBCs/100 WBCs RBC morphology: Moderate polychromasia, 3+ target cells, few schistocytes Which of the following additional laboratory tests would yield informative diagnostic information for this patient?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate laboratory data with other laboratory data to assess test results/3"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Hematology Problem-Solving"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}